>> SATO: First is entitled as PC-BSD uh
FreeBSD on the desktop by Matt Orlander
from iXSystems, so we - please
>> MATT: Thank you. Good morning
I'd like to thank Sato-San and George and the rest
of the AsiaBSDCon organizers for inviting us out
We have a little FreeBSD table
and have brought some goodies like
little beasties
you can put in your pocket and walk around Tokyo
and scare people with
Uh, any BSD committers, come on up, and we have
T-shirts for you
and it'll cost - for free - just to say thank
you
Uh, this is
FreeBSD on the Desktop
I'm lucky enough to have -
Chris Moore, the founder of the PC-BSD
project here
so really, I don't know why I'm
giving this talk Chris
well, my name is Matt Olander
I've been working with BSD since 1998
when I - uh -
I installed a BSD OS installation at a
little server company in San Jose California
called Telenet System Solutions
later on, I ended up
working full time there
and that they eventually got acquired by BSDi
and so I went on to continue working there
BSDi sold their software assets to WindRiver
and the hardware company lived on with a group
of employees that bought it out
and eventually changed our name back to iXsystems
and now we are very involved trying to support
the FreeBSD project
as well as the other BSDs
I'm on the FreeBSD marketing team
some would say that I don't do enough for that
and of course I do some PC-BSD project
management as well
so people ask us a lot of times why did we do PC-BSD
Chris can give you
a really good answer about
how he wanted to convert his Mom
and he tried actually to do this
on Linux at first and Linux is such
a fragmented mass, it was much easier for
him to turn to BSD and focus on one
core project
%uh the other reason I usually give is because I
chicks dig BSD
as you can see
that's PC-BSD babe - I don't know if you
can read it
but her site is pcbsdbabe.com
and she was a girl
that installed PC-BSD on one of the early
releases and loved it so much that she
she started a blog
it is pretty entertaining
I won't pull it up here
what is the PC-BSD - I meant to delete that, I swear
PC-BSD it is FreeBSD, but it's not a fork
all we do is take the default FreeBSD
operating system
and add a graphical installer
you know, it's integrated with KDE and
Fluxbox right out of the box
and of course we've got some tools that
Chris and his team have written
to make some of the typical system configuration
utilities a bit easier to use through a GUI
and I'll be showing you some of those
the big claim to fame for PC-BSD
is a different package management system
called PBI
and this is a graphical method of installing
say, like a FreeBSD port or more like a package
in a binary format using a front-end GUI
it contains all the dependencies of the package
in one directory
%uh so that we can save the package through
upgrades and
%uh make it very easy for other users
to install
we're working very hard
to integrate this more closely with FreeBSD's
methodology of ports and packages
and so far
Chris and his team have setup an auto-building PBI server
it's semi-auto, right?
>> CHRIS: it's pretty auto
>> MATT: pretty automatic now
it takes a little manual configuration of a port
and then it tears through the port and generates
the PC-BSD binary
and so now
whenever the port - how many are in their so far now Chris?
>> CHRIS: about a hundred
>> MATT: okay, great. so that's awesome
so I mean you know it's only hundred but
really for desktop use
%uh how many times you know how many applications
are going to be useful
for your average desktop user
%uh power users, you know, %uh
they are familiar with freebsd can just drop in and
install a port or a package so it's not a big deal
so Chris and his team have
setup scripts that tear through
%uh a hundred or so ports so far
and that whenever a port is updated
it will automatically generate the new PC-BSD binary
and then it'll notify all of the PC-BSD users
with an annoying pop-up window
that updates are available
but of course you can turn that off
so you know the goal here is to make it
%uh easier for people to use
FreeBSD that are new to it especially
I think the jury that the PC-BSD community
as I look at forums and talk to people
is Windows users
so we're getting a lot of Windows users coming on over and
I think now we're getting a lot of Linux users coming over
you know, they like Linux, but
they've tried twenty different flavors
they start to realize that
something's wrong
so we're now that at PC-BSD 1.5
which includes Xorg 7.3
3.5.8, actually, you're already bumped up to
like a 1.5.1, right? [mumbles]
as soon as you get back, he's
been working on that at the hotel
we have a new system updater tool
that updates your PC-BSD system
on the fly
how does that work Chris? So you get
notified there's an update and
I got a call from my office in fact yesterday
that they had done that
the KMail call that I had to look into
but it just notifies you and you can just
download an ISO or you can just download a patch
>> CHRIS: it notifies, downloads and applies the
patch to your system
>> MATT: brilliant
>> CHRIS: on the fly
>> MATT: and of course now we have a WiFi tool
which is really cool
it'll scan and you just double click on that
networking
and enter your WPA or WEP key and
it'll remember these
Uh we've got
improvements to the PBI removal tool
which is similar to the add / remove programs
from Windows
so I'll show you that
Uh the new sound detection program
and we now finally have an amd64 build
as of PC-BSD 1.5
so actually that you can follow along in the
your slides
I'm going to drop out of this and show
you the actual installation
it's like a cooking show
okay so here's our first screen after a very
typical looking
FreeBSD bootstrap
and we have different languages and of
course keyboard layouts
and we do have Japanese and I believe that
Chris already installed
the Japanese version, is that right
so you have it running upstairs on the laptop?
oh right here? awesome
I would have done that but then I wouldn't
have been able to read anything
we default to allow submitting
usage statistics to FreeBSD stats
and the reason we do that
is so that when I go to talk to companies
like Adobe
to persuade them to give us a native Flash 9
which Kirk has already appeared out there
this gives me a place I can point them to
start to persuade for the business case
of them supporting
BSD natively
and I think really close to seeing that this
year
I think Desktop BSD are
I guess you can call them our competitor
although we don't really compete
we collaborate a bit
they just now started defaulting to allowing these
statistics and I saw a big jump in their
BSD stats
here is the license agreement, and all we have
here is the BSD license, some of the Intel
firmware licenses,
and then, that's about it
Anyway, I'm going to go ahead and agree
here's where I can do a fresh install
or update my existing system
the update basically
%uh Chris, how does the update work? It TARs up
the user's home directory?
[mumbles]
and we've done it many times at work so far
and it works pretty darn well
so there you see, I didn't enter that correctly,
I was just testing that
so now the passwords match up
I go ahead and enter
a default user
you can choose your shells here
and Chris has added Bash as a default
here as well, because
well, a lot of Linux users seem to prefer Bash
here's where I can toggle auto-login,
the Windows people
they're used to it
here's your partitioning
Chris has changed the partitioning a little bit
we used to have something where you actually could go in
and really tweak the partitioning and people were
breaking things and so right now
it is kind of turned off for now
oh you can still do that, ok
what about what about adding
a partitioning tool something that
>> CHRIS: we've talked about it
>> MATT: it's dangerous, it's really dangerous
I'm going to go ahead, since I'm actually on a Mac,
I'm going to use the entire disk
I could customize and go setup my own
partitioning scheme
Chris, when are you going to bring back the server edition?
when we have enough tools to throw at it?
>> CHRIS: we don't have enough tools
>> MATT: what it was
we had a server edition
and we removed it as it wasn't really doing much yet
and basically it dropped you into a default
Fluxbox install
with minimal tools
so you could tweak it
once we bring that back, we'll have %uh
we'll have, based on iXsystems
based on the company's, the sponsors that
come out here
we'll throw together some default partitionings
that we see a lot of
as we %uh, as we ship out servers
and then have them in there as an option
like a LAMP server, a mail server, a DNS or what
have you
this is cool
so now I can go ahead and choose add-ons
and add them on to the system
it's a short list right now
but you've got some cool stuff
I grabbed the source in ports
we have %uh
Opera
they agreed within in forty eight hours
when I asked them
that we could ship with
their Opera binary
they said absolutely no problem
and Adobe agreed that we could ship with Flash
so we do
if you select any of these
%uh I'd have to insert the second disc
so I'll go ahead and skip it
and then, there you go
very secure
so we'll let this cook
so now like the cooking show
I put it in the oven
but I already have one finished
and so here's a finished PC-BSD installation
this is very close to what you would see by default
although I've already gone and installed a few things
noticeably
on the right this is a very %uh this is very
very cool when I show %uh
Windows web developers in particular love this
we can install what we call PAMP
I'm trying to come up with a better name
but for now it's PAMP
and that would of course by the
Apache, MySQL and PHP stack
what's interesting is
the guy, I don't know who wrote this for us
someone did this for us
you did it?
I do know the guy who did it
%uh I thought someone else did it originally?
did you update it? yeah? okay, great
this was great
I just took a class at UC Santa Cruz
I showed the teacher this
and she had me show the entire class
once I had showed her
in literally two clicks
we install %uh Apache, PHP, MySQL
and then we get some nice little icons
%uh to start and to stop
we can %uh
just instantly switch
the PHP versions
with the %uh you know web devs really like
for testing
you get a little drop down to switch the version
especially, I noticed that even in this class
these guys are you know CSS wizards
and xHTML wizards and
they've never seen a command line
and so
everyone was looking at you know
this is my Mac that I use for testing
but I have a PC-BSD laptop
as well
for work
this is my personal Mac
but for work I use my PC-BSD laptop
and so I had that at the class
and I was able to share and
everyone was like what the
hell are you doing?
and so I gave them a quick demo
and %uh
you see here we can put a little icon
down in the tray
that lets us easily start and stop and monitor
the services
%uh for someone that's not familiar
with how these work
we can even go in and edit
the httpd.conf
or the php.ini
and so this is just one of the one hundred
packages that we have building
and this is a really cool one
and then they can open the web root
or open their personal web root
or toggle the web sites around
so a pretty clever tool for manipulating
Apache, MySQL and PHP
via the GUI
and it installs that %uh that
MySQL GUI admin tool that I've never used
yeah yeah they love that stuff
everyone in the class knew what that was
and I was like, what?
now let me show you the big deal
this is a PBI
that I downloaded
off of PBIDir.com
so this is the this is the GIMP
and I'm going to install it
on a very fresh installation
the icon you get in the upper left hand corner
says Get PBIs and %uh
and it just opens up a Konqueror window
directly to the website
I've been talking to Chris about
maybe in the future
having the %uh
maybe grabbing the Desktop BSD's port tool
having that on a tab
and then having a PBI add / remove
on the other tab so that you can just browse
all the programs that you can install
via a port, package or PBI
on one single interface
so I'm going to install the GIMP
I'm going to agree to that nasty license
I love these graphics that Kinsalez does
ok and finished
and there you go
we got the GIMP on there
and it created of course a
menu icon
in here as well
under the GIMP
so now I could easily upgrade this
in fact when the PBI gets updated it will
notify me
that hey there's a new GIMP do you
want to download and install it right now?
and you just click yes and it
downloads and installs
and keeps %uh
your GIMP preferences or whatever
the application preferences that you
already have in there
and then since we're targeting mostly
you know, easy to use
desktop operating systems specifically
for Windows users so we have
a lot of familiar tools for them
if you go into the Start menu and look
at the settings, and here's my software
there's the add / remove that I was telling you about
and so I'll go in and
we will remove it
so here's all the software I have installed
you can see the GIMP there
and really since the GIMP
is really just installed in our
own little directory structure here
so you can see
the GIMP and
all its libs
are hiding in here
that's the %uh, I don't know if you can see that
but it's the automatic directory structure that's created
from the scripts that we use on the auto-building server
and so I go ahead and click remove
and of course all this is really doing
is an rm -rf on there
and bam - gone
and there's a little script
that pulls the icons out of there
and notifies you that it is gone
and we've got a services manager
this is actually PC-BSD 1.4
but we've got 1.5 running upstairs
that didn't have any PBIs to show on 1.5
and so here, of course,
anyone who has used Windows you can
see this looks very similar to whatever
that Windows tool is called
so we can start / stop services
that are enabled in the start-up
and so you know
it’s not like this can replace a system administrator
but it sure %uh
well I know that everyone at our office
runs this of course
and most of our family members now are running it
and I was down at
the Luxor in Las Vegas
and I was wearing my FreeBSD shirt
and I'm sitting at the pub
and this guy goes
you've heard of FreeBSD?
and I go 'yeah, dude'
he goes have you heard of PC-BSD?
and I thought it was really cool that
this random bartender down in Vegas is
telling me about PC-BSD. I go 'yeah,
I've heard of that'.
he goes 'we're running that at home, dude, it's cool'
so I went into the room and got some swag
for him and he was so happy
we've got our own users tool
we've got a WiFi tool
%uh
Why don't we do our own user management tool
over the KDE one?
>> CHRIS: it was the only sensible option
>> MATT: yeah
you know we're trying to get closer involved
with the KDE guys
so that they test a little more on FreeBSD
because we've discovered some of their stuff
just doesn't compile
or work properly
and we have to create BSD-specific tools for them
it would be nicer if we had a little
more collaboration there
there's your online update manager where I can
go
and manually check for updates
and install them
and I've got my %uh
my network settings
which pulls up the WiFi tool which is really
easy to use. I don't think it'll pull up
because my Mac
doesn't translate it
but it's pretty darn easy to use
actually, this is the old one huh?
we've got the new one upstairs
it's even better
almost done
ah yes, so we didn't see this yet
this is the X window configurator
and so this is really cool if you've
got a supported 3D graphics card
you can go ahead
and select it here
and be running Beryl right at startup
so when we do trade shows
which is part of what I do
to evangelize FreeBSD
we bring along a 32 inch LCD
and we throw PC-BSD up there with Beryl
running in it, and boy people just go
nuts over it
over those windows
you know, those squares, Beryl stuff
I'm over it already, but
and there's the boot screen
and the update manager
I've already covered the update
there's looking for a new PBI update
this was the test you were running for the FireFox
one before you rolled it out
so I was testing it and grabbing screenshots
and then it installed it and then
it told me it was finished
sure enough it fired right up
and worked like a charm
so, very cool
we just did this
in fact
the GIMP and we removed it
so, how can you help?
well you could grab a CD
today and install PC-BSD
and certainly one of the biggest contributions
any user can do
is reporting bugs back to us
I noticed, I don't know, last month
I think people had reported just a really small
list of bugs, but you troll the forums and
they're complaining in there
so you go on and say, please report the bug
where we will see it
because we can't be
trolling ten thousand posts every day
that would be one way you could help
documentation and translations
it would be nice if
%uh
I don't know, who did our Japanese translation?
we don't even know
it would be cool if a Japanese native speaker
could take a look at it and say
'hey, there are some errors here'
%uh
maybe it was a
%uh a British or an American guy who speaks Japanese
and maybe he made some mistakes
%uh pass some CDs out, download them, tell your friends
get your Mom on it
and prepare for all the phone calls
and of course evangelize
if you can do C, Qt, or Shell programming
we can always use help there
and you can just email the folk
or go to the forums
or the PC-BSD web site and see how to contact us
and there we have a core team list there very
similar to FreeBSD
so you can email the core team of PC-BSD
and everyone will see that
alright, so that's PC-BSD in a nutshell
does anyone have any questions 'cause we have Chris in the room
yes?
>> AUDIENCE MEMBER: like, so %uh
[unclear]
most of the computer is like a desktop
you know, it's an old computer
so, %uh, does this system have a
driver for the, like, the sound card
>> MATT: well this is FreeBSD 6.3 so
yeah, absolutely, FreeBSD
supports the older hardware really really well
from my experience
any other questions?
we have the FreeBSD table upstairs
so stop on by before I drink too much sake!
what's the latest on BSD stats?
I mean, there's always a certain
percentage of people
that turn off the reporting
for some weird reason
last month we had ten thousand installs
so you know - how many of those keep?
it's really hard to say, right
Yes?
>> AUDIENCE MEMBER: Matt, two questions
I'm from China
does FreeBSD or PC-BSD support Chinese?
>> CHRIS: we've had people translate into Chinese, yes
>> AUDIENCE MEMBER: we are interested in this project
because we have some Linux consumers
we've tried to persuade them to use PC-BSD instead
>> MATT: this, this is great, we'd love to help you out
especially convincing Linux consumers
>> AUDIENCE MEMBER: can we join this team?
>> MATT: yes absolutely
we would love to have you
>> AUDIENCE MEMBER: finally, can
PC-BSD have an graphic login interface like KDM?
>> MATT: yeah, it already does, it already does
so on the install, you just uncheck auto-login
and then it'll pull up with a customized KDM
>> AUDIENCE MEMBER: final question,
Is PC-BSD one disc?
>> MATT: yeah, I just install off
of this one disc
the second disc contains some optional
yes, some optional components as well as
some language translations
but yeah, if you want to change the language
during the install you would need the second disc
>> AUDIENCE MEMBER: can we contact
you after the conference?
>> MATT: absolutely and I would love it
we just had a school, an entire school district
in France switch over to PC-BSD so %uh
we're doing a case study
so we can throw that up on the FreeBSD site
they were ecstatic
yeah, they were absolutely ecstatic
and were all like, how can we help?
so all the servers in the city in France
were already on FreeBSD
so when the school district contacted
them to talk about
upgrading their Windows installs
they said why don't we do a test run
with the PC-BSD and see how you guys like it
and they said that the teachers and students loved it
so they rolled it out
and they rolled it out without having any issues
%uh we asked them, you know, I sent them a
bunch of questions and they responded
you know, what kind of issues did you have
how did you solve them?
how do you do upgrades
and so on and so on
the iXsystems marketing girl is
synthesizing that into a case study that
we'll release shortly
absolutely
yes, Jason?
>> JASON: are there things like, %uh
remote home directories
to take your school example are
so students login to one PC and
they have the same home directory?
>> AUDIENCE MEMBER: like Terminal Server?
>> JASON: well, not necessarily a Terminal Server
but more, I don't know, let's go down the Windows path
what do they call it? they call it a Domain server
where you can bounce your home directories
>> AUDIENCE MEMBER: because it's all just FreeBSD
under the hood so you could
>> MATT: yeah, we don't have any
graphical tools right now for that
but any FreeBSD sys admin
could make it sit up and beg
what we are working on
right now some cool PXE stuff
so you'll be able to
boot off of a live CD
and then install tons of machines
from that one installation
so that's pretty cool
any other questions
>> AUDIENCE MEMBER: when are you
planning the next PC-BSD release?
>> CHRIS: 1.6 we're aiming for the end
of the summer to base the first one
off FreeBSD 7
ideally, we'd like to use ZFS as well
>> MATT: KDE4 has a few bugs
so I think we should probably
wait for 4.1
I've been reporting tons of them
[unclear question]
yes and PC-BSD 1.6 will %uh
include support for ZFS
with the front-end to it
and I don't want to put you on the spot
and %uh jails
I don't want to put you on the spot
that'd be cruel
okay well, come see us at the
table thank you very much